[Music]
this is part of rebel wisdoms
sense-making series in the first film
called what is going on I talked about
how the pandemic had acted a bit like a
catalyst and an amplifier of what was
already there the psychologist stanislav
grof talked about altered states and
especially psychedelics as nonspecific
amplifiers just making everything more
intense whether good or bad so if this
has been a bit of a joint psychedelic
trip how do we navigate it I thought the
best person to speak to was Erik Davis
who's one of the foremost historians of
psychedelic culture he's the author of
many different books including high
weirdness where he looks at three key
figures in the counterculture movement
Robert Anton Wilson Terence Mckenna and
philip k dick and this is what he had to
say Eric really good thank you for
making time for the conversation yeah no
good to be here cool so the reason I'm
really keen to talk to you Eric is that
you're one of the kind of foremost
historians of weirdness strangeness and
the sort of the pioneers of that in the
60s and 70s and since this pandemic has
kind of been ramping up and so much has
changed I've had this real sense of the
pandemic and the lockdown as this sort
of nonspecific amplifier I'm reminded of
Stan Grof stanislav grof the amazing
psychologist and pioneer of psychedelic
therapy talked about psychedelics as a
nonspecific amplifier so it just made
everything more intense and it feels a
lot like this is what's been happening
in our culture I want to start just
asking you what we'll get onto some of
the the figures from the 60s and 70s and
what we might be able to learn from them
but what what do you feel about that
frame like the pandemic and this kind of
time we're going through as a
nonspecific amplifier I think it's a
wonderful frame in the sense that it it
forces us to reflect on our own
reactions at least as much as our ideas
about what are what's causing those
reactions he's a way saying the
experience is not caused by LSD
causes your experiences your own set and
setting your own even physiological set
being stimulated by this nonspecific or
amplified by this nonspecific factor so
what that means with acid is it's like
don't go oh the LSD told me this or the
LSD made me do this or so it's more like
wow I have now an opportunity to see how
I respond or what gets amplified when
I'm in encounter this particular
marvelous chemical so if I have a great
psyche death you know if I have a
visionary experience that's something of
mine if I have a hell trip it's
something I have to kind of reflect on
and so in that sense I think it's a
really wonderful way to but again to
push it back on to our own reactions
meaning both how we're processing and
thinking about what's happening out
there but it also I think helps explain
the Sur reality or weirdness of the
situation we're in because it's not like
there's a specific event that we're all
reacting to more or less the same it's
that there's a nebulous largely
invisible you know distributed event
that actually I don't really see too
much in my life I see the signs of it or
how other people are interpreting it but
it's very nebulous it's like a invisible
bomb went off and we're kind of in the
the you know the aftershock of it but we
don't we can't really locate where did
it happen what's going on and so there's
a there's a surreal quality to it
because you can you're you have to kind
of navigate other people's projections
and fears and narratives even as you're
sort of struggling to come up with your
own and resist ones that are starting to
over you know overly impinge on you or
being attracted to ones that make you
feel more afraid and you're like they're
so we're in a kind of lightly
psychedelic state where there's multiple
narratives multiple multiple
possibilities multiple emotional
reactions that have a kind of excessive
surreal dreamlike quality even the way
that
these polarized political events have
just finally revealed that the sort of
media as some kind of coherent
maintainer of consensus reality is just
gone really I mean there are individuals
and individual organs that are doing
good work and you know it's complicated
but the overall sense that we have now
entered into some kind of media
implosion is also part of this sense of
the surreal so it is also an interesting
kind of opportunity to like
pedal-to-the-metal with your spiritual
practice your psychological practice
your like like this is where clear clear
thinking starts to actually have an
active feedback process that improves
the quality of your life and improves
your ability to not be swamped by what's
going on and to me you know you can you
don't need to invoke psychedelics to
talk about that sort of intelligence or
that sort of process or practice at all
but in my life it is partly about having
been a psychedelic person for a very
long time and going through very strange
experiences and quasi psychotic
experiences and dangerous experiences
and delightful experiences and
processing that that has come to allow
me to a certain kind of flexibility
around both nightmare scenarios paranoid
scenarios but also a sense of the almost
humour of being in the midst of
difficult situations and just plunging
forward with a certain kind of Jawad avi
and also a celebration of the ways that
people can come together who are
similarly going through difficult
situations and you can actually improve
the quality of your communication and of
your perception of the world and even if
that perception can be very difficult
yeah I mean there's so much to pick up
on and what you were just saying but the
one thing that really came through
partly but when you were talking about
the media as well is this sort of sense
of narrative collapse but I also wanted
to bring in the concept of spiritual
emergency because this is again coming
from Stan Grof is probably the one who's
done the most work on this but the sense
of the
we're in a kind of medical paradigm that
that often pathologize --is altered
states often pathologize a spiritual
experience and he came up with the
concept of spiritual emergency to talk
about anything that didn't an altered
state or a transformational process that
didn't really fit into a Western medical
model and would often be labeled as SCI
psychosis or mania or some of those and
it feels I've had experiences like that
or I understand and I understand a lot
of what that feels like
and often what I found that would come
up in those spiritual emergencies
there's a lot of the buried stuff from
the past stuff that I hadn't dealt with
from childhood or stuff that I hadn't
dealt with from my my upbringing my
conditioning and it feels to me
especially in the last few weeks where
we see all of this repressed stuff from
the American culture from the British
culture just coming up it feels to me
like the the entire culture is in the
middle of some kind of spiritual
emergency would you would you agree with
that you sort of seen the same kind of
yeah I mean I I would because they in a
way spiritual emergency is the best
model you have to as an alternate to
break down in psychosis I mean that's
kind of what he's saying he's saying
look if you have somebody maybe they're
tripping or maybe they're not even
tripping they're just going through a
point part of their life and they start
to have these symptoms that conventional
science is going to say or medicine is
going to say oh they're psychotic or
they're bipolar he want Groth wanted to
say look there's another way of framing
it and there was a lot of stuff like
that in the 60s and 70s it was a whole
anti-psychiatry moment there was a whole
attempt to reframe difficult altered
states as potentially valuable as even
trauma you know that that's actually a
very interesting thing a very important
difference between our era now and that
era that people don't talk about enough
that's really key to understand if
you've taught if you're thinking in
terms of that connection and then I'll
go on more about now is in a sense a lot
of people in the 60s embraced trauma as
a rite of passage
into a new state so the idea that taking
a huge dose of psychedelics is going to
tear you apart it opens up the
possibility you walk out on the other
side and you've left a lot of stuff
behind a lot of the ideas about having
extraordinary experience enlightenment
experience in fact that eras whole quest
for radical intense experiences was
partly justified because lots of people
you know people on the street
psychiatrists people at Esalen etc etc
had this idea that there was a kind of a
cleansing craziness at the far end of
which was the opportunity to reconstruct
in a new way and we don't think that way
anymore you know we are much more scared
about trauma and how trauma you can't
get out of it or it tears things down
and there's we're not you know we're
almost on the opposite where we don't
even want to trigger past trauma and
that those two differences are very
important they help explain a lot of the
ways that to them contemporary discourse
around psychedelics is so different than
it used to be but I think it's also in
some ways not setting us up as well as
it could be for what we're going through
because what we're going through like
you say does have the character of some
return of the repressed or some kind of
now I have to actually look at not just
aspects of myself but aspects of reality
it's like if you've if you've kind of
been in your bubble your whole life and
then finally you have the opportunity to
really absolutely
existentially recognize that you are
going to die and you can't layer
anything on top of it that is a
traumatic experience or can be you can
also be an illuminating experience and
there can be illumination in the trauma
and that's it gets really complicated
one of the things that I'm talking about
with all three of the characters that I
write about it I think one of the things
that's sort of unique about my approach
is that a lot of counts they will either
stress the psychopathology or the stress
the spirituality so you take someone
like Alan Watts
you know when Alan Watts comes off as a
really groovy mellow guys on top of him
stuff but his actual life is kind of a
mad
in some ways he was sort of a dark
character and you know whatever it's
complicated but he you know he was an
alcoholic he died of alcoholism he was a
womanizer he was you know he had a lot
of issues with control or self-control
and so when you start to look at the
philosophy you go huh what's going on
here it gets complicated but some most
people would either say you know some
dark but negative biographers who go oh
he was just a reprobate he couldn't deal
with it and all everything else was just
a justification for that and then a lot
of the kind of you know spiritual
new-age thing they don't think about
that they just talk about his brilliant
ideas but it's a mix it's on a continuum
and the three guys that I talk about
they are they all spend time in
something like psychosis or something
like paranoid pathology some some quite
repeatedly in the case of philip k dick
but they also were spiritual figures
they also had prophetic visionary
experiences that had integrity and
consequence and richness they also all
reflected philosophically on things and
and that there's a continuum there and
so you the fact that there's psychosis
in the picture or the fact that there's
social breakdown or the fact that there
is a big uptick in mental disturbance
doesn't mean just the whole thing is
unraveling it also means there are other
possibilities that are open and I you
know a more positive view of let's say
in the United States in the last few
weeks the extraordinary energy of these
demonstrations which which have a
different character than the many
demonstrations throughout my whole life
I've been going to demonstrations but
there's this futility around them they
seem stale there's something we haven't
we done this already but these are
different you know there's something
else is kind of constellated so I think
spiritual emergency is a great way to
look at it and I again it's also because
I do think that in a non narcissistic
way this is a spiritual opportunity and
I say that because spirituality has been
hijacked in the last couple of decades
by narcissistic consumes of consumerism
not entirely but many things that
started out at the very
Lisa's kind of interesting playful
creative spaces yoga in America whatever
you know all these things you could just
watch as they became more successful
they allowed people to actually close
off and kind of enter into their own
little world view and sort of pamper
themselves and and hide in a way in
their hip Nisour in their whatever it is
and right now it's like okay you got are
you guys still into your spirituality
you're still doing your yoga still doing
your practice still doing your
psychedelics still you know doing your
celebrations well if you are now you're
either not completely disconnected
because you're not paying attention to
the crisis in the world or you're having
to read you know reconstitute the
connections between your practices in
the world in a way that I think can
actually help both sides of the equation
so we're actually at a point where
things that have been sort of absorbed
into business as usual consumerism as
usual narcissistic social media
self-promotion as usual now are like
okay we're here you know actually we can
be used in different ways in one of the
ways that that happens is that
spirituality is a way to get you through
spiritual emergency another way of
saying that is that religion in the
broadest sense particularly religious
practices not so much the ideas or
ideology reading this your belief about
Jesus or whatever but the practices the
daily practices the the processes of
emotion of how do you process other
people that kind of that kind of world
that stuff you know is is in a way
designed to deal with psycho with our
own psychopathological capacity it's
it's not that you know people you know
people make that point they'll say oh
look at religion it's just kind of OCD
you know look at those guys they have
their little rituals they do every day
and and you know it's just you know it's
it's just sort of a regressive form of
behavior why don't we look at the other
way which is actually that's a way of
dealing with our own capacities to go
crazy or to lose the plot or to break
down or to weep or to I mean not
weepings bad but I mean to like you know
in in terrible gruta nameless grief aunt
really get out of and so I feel like are
my opportunity our time round was also
an opportunity to reframe a lot of these
practices as you know tools for survival
you've spent probably as long as anyone
looking at weirdness altered states and
the kind of the people who navigated
that in the sixties and seventies who do
you think are the key people to pay
attention to and what do you think of
the best tips for kind of navigating the
space that we're in now well you know
it's funny I started out really just
being interested in the problem of how
do individuals deal with these
extraordinary bizarre experiences work
that are sort of equally composed of
psychosis and religion and in kind of
looking at what they were doing I I felt
like I figured out some navigational
tips that weirdly seemed to apply to
much more things than I thought I was
talking about initially and one of those
things is what I call the tightrope walk
and so in all three of the cases that I
was looking at in high weirdness a
philip k dick terence mckenna and Robert
Anton Wilson they're all having these
bizarre experience it's not always from
the same time two of them took a lot of
psychedelics dick didn't take too much
psychedelics he was more of a natural
but in any case they were spending a lot
of time in these visionary worlds with
paranoid implications and loads of
synchronicities and you know they were
really getting on out on the edge but
unlike a lot of people who are either
typical paranoids or religious
visionaries they also kind of resisted
what they were experiencing and they did
it partly through humor and they did it
partly through skepticism and this is to
me one of the really important
transformations that happens with
psychedelic experience is that up to
psychedelic experience most people who
have visionary experiences that don't
just become completely crazy they tend
to really believe them that's kind of
the history of religion as you
have like this extraordinary experience
and you're like I had this experience I
was talking to an angel he gave me a
book let's go for it you know and
whether it's you know people in you know
the 19th century or back in ancient in
the ancient world but psychedelics
introduce a new thing in the equation
which is that you can have an
extraordinary visionary experience with
religious implications apocalyptic
implications messianic implications that
you know I know I see the world and then
you wake up the next day to go whoa what
was that
and you kind of how most have a choice
do you hold on to that visionary
conviction or do you go okay something
more is going on here or that has to
also be integrated into this or what do
we do what do we do with this and that
was part of my questions what do we do
with this so I was interested in in the
way that these guys also resisted it and
it has to do with this quality of
skepticism and with what I would call
ordinary reason and I like to
distinguish reason from rationality like
to me the way I'm using it right here
right now rationality is kind of like an
attempt to to support and understand
these large systems of explanations that
can account for a greater and greater
percentage of reality so you're like I'm
into whatever it's mathematics its
logical relations these large systems
that help us understand the world and
I'm not saying that those systems aren't
groovy but that's not what I'm talking
about by reason I mean something that's
a little bit more close to home it's
like is this gonna be good for me is
it's not gonna be good for me what if I
do that it's gonna be this and it's like
hi I feel this about this person but I
don't really trust it I think I might be
running one of my own trips you know
that kind of sense of bringing a
skeptical quality to your own experience
as a way to help you navigate through
life better and that quality these guys
all had in really interesting ways not
all the time sometimes they lost the
plot but a lot of time they were able to
go through these extremely bizarre
experiences but kind of keep their feet
on the ground and the
for I came up with this that I think is
actually very helpful for us is this
idea of being on on a tightrope you know
you're no longer on solid ground in some
sense your own responses create the
gravity that allows you not to fall and
you've got this nice instrument and the
instrument is kind of like ordinary
reason it's like well it might be this
well I don't know about that look that's
a little bit much and so you kind of
keep your own interior balance of
awareness your eyes are open you're
responding to all the shifts of the
situation you're in you've got your
hands on some of the stuff you really
know things about psychology things
about you know how the mind processes
things certain skeptical ideas about
believing over believing our own
experiences a certain quality of kind of
organic skepticism and then with all
that you can go farther and farther and
farther into the screaming void and that
is a kind of that's that's a good handy
tip for for you know far out voyaging
and psychedelics it's a handy tip for
when you you're losing the plot for
whatever reason you synchronicities
crazy stuff in your life terrible grief
when you start to kind of really lose
connection with things you're like oh
here we go
there's still these threads of of a
certain kind
okay now I'm on the tight rope now I
gotta like try to do my best I can
sometimes you fall but then you get to
get it back up most of the time and I
really think that this was something
that these guys were kind of exploring
and another analogy for that you get in
Robert Anton Wilson that I also think is
really applicable to two today two
aspects of today particularly if you're
thinking about conspiracy theory and how
easily it is for people to get absorbed
into conspiracy narratives today which
is a fascinating thing it's it's for me
under trying to grapple with conspiracy
theory today and I admit that the term
conspiracy theory is problematic and we
have to NIST or assign it and it doesn't
mean there are conspiracies bah-bah-bah
it's always important to say these
things because there's a lot of
mainstream talk about conspiracy theory
that's really pretty stupid but for me
it's a really grapple with it in its
complexity is not just like a sidelight
it's not like oh yeah all the deplorable
is over here getting into conspiracy
theory you know all the smart people are
trying to keep the ship going it's not
like that it's much more symptomatic and
it's much more central I think to as a
sign of what's happening with media with
consensus reality with the narrative
wars with weaponized multi-layered
narratives where certain areas to put
forward to because they feed these other
narratives that are being controlled
from a third position you know all of
those scary you know spy movie
psychedelic paranoia kinds of zones
that's just part of the fabric of
reality now so we got to get good at
navigating this stuff and not just
trying to put it in a box and Wilson was
was pretty good at navigating his stuff
you know you could critique him in some
ways in some ways he he was probably a
little bit he probably played with the
gullible a little bit more than he
should have but you know in any case he
was definitely someone who was trying to
walk with his tightrope walk is a
tightrope walker into these realms and
one thing he talked about was this place
that people find themselves in called
Chapel perilous and what Chapel perilous
was it's a it's from the Grail myth
myths but in Wilson's interpretation
it's basically a place where you've been
following these strange lines of
implication you going down rabbit holes
in the internet or you know the other
earlier forms of archives or your own
psychedelic experience or your own dream
life and synchronicities and
everything's starting to connect and you
know you're then you find yourself in
this place where you can't go back
you're like oh oh the doors shut behind
me I can't just go oh this is all a bit
much I'll just going to return to my
ordinary life because the implications
are too much the narrative has swallowed
you up and he says like when you're in
Chapel perilous there's only two ways
out you either come out
cold paranoid or you come out a radical
agnostic and there's a lot of wisdom in
that a lot of wisdom in that
and because radical agnostic if we want
to avoid the stone-cold paranoid which
unfortunately it feels like a lot of
people aren't then we have to move you
can't go back you have to go forward and
what does that mean that means even more
skepticism the problem one of the main
problems that a lot of conspiracy theory
people go through it's um it's something
that a writer on on the net described as
freshmen skepticism which is that you
learn the first stage of radical
skepticism about the narratives you've
gotten the media the stories it's like
you know who says were we're on a three
dimensional ball floating through the
earth like you know maybe these guys
have been lying to us all the time so
you you learn that the real power of
skepticism which is an extraordinary
it's like an acid it just eats through
everything and you use it just enough to
get pull away from a consensus view and
then where are you well then you're like
locked into some weird internet
subculture you know longtail
echo-chamber
and then you're like yeah I'm home I
found my tribe and and you find these
people and they just iterate the same
stuff you've heard from the guy next to
them so they haven't freed themselves
from collective narratives from
collective stories a lot of them they
just get away from the first layer and
get stuck in the second but the radical
agnostic goes well how do I why should I
trust this weird guy over here and with
his videos why do I trust these
conspiracy narratives why do I trust my
own fear and and so there's a way of
going deeper and deeper and deeper into
skepticism where you pop out and you're
like okay I I really can't really ground
any of my beliefs I can see the way that
mathematics has these self contradictory
elements to them I can see the way that
you know physics is contradictory in all
sorts of ways and which physics are we
talking about
and will there ever be one physics
unlikely you realize how multiplicities
how chaotic how multi-dimensional the
world is but you're ok with that because
you're you're kind of back you're back
with a difference you're back with like
well but I'm in this condition where I'm
making decisions I'm building models of
the world I'm talking to people that I
can resonate with and we're helping each
other
clarify how we get through that you know
science can give us a lot of information
about what's going on but you hold
everything more lightly you hold
everything sort of gingerly and you're
aware that it can go south or turn under
or the rug can be pulled out from under
you at any time so that when that
happens you're not terrified you don't
lose the plot you're like oh it's the
crazy part again or oh now I'm paranoid
today yeah I'm Reese all coming together
ok well let's try to navigate this be be
nice to people don't hurt myself you
know it in a weird way it comes back to
being very pragmatic and very realistic
but you're not clinging onto these
totalizing narratives anymore and that's
where people get stuck because that's
scary I mean it's scary to believe that
Bill Gates is making a vaccine that
we're gonna he's gonna force us all to
take and it's got a microchip and
they're gonna control us yeah that's
pretty scary it's like a weird fiction
or I love all I love weird fiction I
love horror I love science fiction you
know it's another one of those and it's
scary if you think it's true but it's a
lot scarier to go in some ways the world
is a chaos that nobody knows is really
going on nobody knows and if you think
that there's a captain of the ship and
you finally get there and you get into
the the captain's chamber it's empty
there's just committees and and fights
and negotiations and different models
and that's us riding history riding this
flowing chaos of a wave and there you
are waking up to it you know having
ultimate responsibility but also
realizing you don't know what's going on
and that's a very psychedelic moment
and you then there's the next day how
are you gonna live with that well get
out of Chapel perilous man
get in get into like if that's the way
you've gone embrace radical agnosticism
embrace not knowing but not not a one
that forced that and this enables you
from making decisions it's it's it's a
paradox in a way but not totally and
it's to my mind a very it's like a
mature psychedelia or a mature kind of a
skepticism where you're you're going for
it but you don't stop from from you know
taking all the way down and then having
to come back because there you are
you're still making decisions do I do
this do I do that you can't just say I
don't know it's all of its all fake or
whatever doesn't work
so that's my hope you know or it's and
it's not for everybody it's just for
people I think who find themselves going
in these weird ways that as I said with
conspiracy theory are now just part of
mediated reality so you have people who
have no psychedelic experience who don't
think about this these ways it does
don't know the history of conspiracy
theory just tuning into this stuff and
really getting lost really fast and I
know people personally I've seen a lot
of people in the new-age world and the
yoga world and the psychedelic world
Burning Man world all these worlds that
I'm kind of part in and part out just
lose the plot get gets get absorbed into
narratives that are being manipulated by
other levels of narrative and other
players for very specific reasons so
it's a time for for some of these tools
to to spread yeah yeah it's really
interesting I mean we did a whole series
on conspiracy so I kind of looked into
it and there's something it is very
psychoactive the whole the whole area of
conspiracy theory is very psychoactive
and one of the best summaries of why
that is came from a friend of mine who
says that it's a lot of it is very
archetypal material we're moving into
we're moving into like mythopoetic
realms and if you're not careful at some
you actually start chasing Satan like
there's there's all of these kind of
really deep religious archetypes and for
example like projecting Satan onto Bill
Gates classic one that you sort of see
people doing constantly online but at
the same time you can't reject it
wholesale either because a friend of
mine also said that this in some sense
becoming a conspiracy theories theorist
is probably a necessary initiation for
all of us
like when once we let go of consensus
reality going through that process is
almost like a necessary initiation now I
I think that's I think that's really
true
another thing that that reminds me of is
what one of the things I was trying to
do in in high weirdness when I was
looking at all the stories and visions
and books that these Psychonauts had had
come up with is to take them seriously
but not take them literally and the the
instinctive mainstream respond to
conspiracy is to not take its literally
or seriously or you go over the other
side you take it seriously and you take
it literally and then a lot of things
have been have been set up so it's one
of those in a way it's another aspect of
this practice of agnosticism where I
like I go into it and I go no there's
something here what is it what is that
for and part of it I think is a
revelation of these archetypal
narratives these unconscious fears and
phantasms like Satan like the end of the
world like the saved remnant and a lot
of them by the way are Christian and I
think that part of the problem with
conspiracy theory is that how to say
this is that it initiates you into a
kind of realm of the imaginal that again
we have to take seriously that it's not
just fantasies or you know dream
patterns in some dusty book that like
the imaginal is no joke it's part of our
world it's part of who we are and you
get in there and you're like whoa what's
going on here and there are certain
patterns that have humans have used to
kind of organize it and the Christian
one has a certain has
some features of it that make it
attractive and one of those is that it's
very clear there's a good and an evil
and I'm on the good side and then that
gives me a purpose in life which is to
spread the message of good and evil so
now I'm gonna propagate the conspiracy
theory and it's all in relationship to a
moment in the near future where
everything is going to come apart or
it's all going to be revealed you know
in UFO stuff they talk about disclosure
and UFO folks have been talking about
disclosure for decades and we get a
little bits of it you know it's the
authorities even play with it they give
you you know the Air Force gives you a
few bits and you're like that's it
disclosure is just around the corner but
it's a it's a pattern it's a way of
organizing history that's very rooted in
a kind of Christian way of looking at it
I prefer a more shamanic view of the
imaginal world and I think that that is
a more mature psychedelically informed
kind of view and that's one in which
you're like welcome to a world with many
ambiguous players what looks like evil
may not be so evil what looks like good
may not be so good and you and yours
have to kind of navigate this through
alliances and practices and your own
sort of autonomous ability to navigate
that zone rather than joining the army
of the good against the army of the
devil and so that's I think a dimension
that's going on with this idea that
you're that you're talking about as I
kind of as a kind of initiation but in a
more grounded way I would also say that
the the way that a lot of conspiracy
theories are true is that they are let's
call them allegories for real conditions
of real power whose implications are
both harrowing enough and difficult
enough to pin down that you can't really
get there through conventional means of
journalism investigative journalism
academic study that it just it sort of
alludes that so that you know the degree
to which
psychopharmacology and and and you know
the corporations that make pill like
that they maintain such a massive
influence over media over our self-image
over our medicine that the very things
we take into our bodies you know from a
alien anthropologist point of view it's
this totally weird you know dark dark
white coded shamanism that has works but
doesn't work and I mean it's so it's so
vast that you can't really get there
with just like you know even if you
follow like the oxycontin trail I go how
did they how did we end up like
addicting millions of Americans with
these powerful drugs that we knew were
bad like how does that happen
and you can go through as an
investigative journalist and track ok
this family these guys made this
decision here's this regulatory agency
here are these lobbyists blah blah blah
and you get this kind of murky it's war
story that never really ends and hardly
anybody ever takes responsibility for it
and that may be the best we can do with
that medium but on another level the
horror of that like the horror of that
where are you gonna put that you put it
in the imagination and so then when you
get a Bill Gates vaccine microchip story
you're like the effect the emotional
energy that is animating that story
that's true that or it's responsive to a
real situation and that's another thing
I that I recommend people who are going
through this realm is to become very
good at picking apart the effect or the
emotion from the narrative and that this
is true of you too like when something
is seems exciting or seems attractive
seems to be true what is it what is it
pulling out of you emotionally not the
story emotionally because a lot of the
manipulation a lot of the narrative
manipulation that we see it has to do
with figuring out which of many stories
are
best able to trigger and capture these
emotions which most of us aren't is
aware of which are sometimes very
powerful fear dread lust resentment
bitterness hatred
I mean powerful stuff we are like crazy
animals and if you get the right
narrative oh I've got it you know and I
learned this listening to a lot of
right-wing radio back in the day you
know be you know be kind of before well
I mean you know it's still continues on
and it's glorious but this was like you
know 20 30 years ago when it was really
just sort of bubbling up and it was
always so interesting because you could
just hear the way the host was sort of
like retelling a story about like
immigrants okay all the immigrants they
come in here and got it
oh wait a Dean now you're getting all
these calls God God these people are
they're done and you realize that it's
not actually about the language or the
concepts or the political models
it's about bitterness and resentment and
powerlessness and fear and stirring that
stuff up and getting it to stick on
certain narratives and that's how a lot
of narrative control happens and so that
also gives you a way of appreciating
what's going on with conspiracy theory
because a lot of the emotions are really
heavy they're really dark it is not an
accident it's very important to
understand that at the heart of queueing
on which is this vast influential you
know right-wing Trump Pro Trump because
I don't II was called right-wing I'll
call Trump conspiracy theory that
actually has you know people who believe
it are running for office for perfect
you know in the federal government right
now as we speak in the United States
then at the heart of this is in some
ways the worst thing that any of us can
imagine the ritualized sexual abuse of
children horrible impossible to think
about without this murky slime of
feeling arising and it's so easy to
weapon
anger self-justification that's it
that's my line in the sand all of that
those emotions that come up out of the
horror of that reality and unfortunately
it is a reality it's part of our human
darkness which will we've never gotten
out of and we're unlikely to ever get
out of but it's not an excuse but it's
just part of it but it's focused in
there because of the way that that
generates so much effect and energy and
emotion so to go into that seriously but
not literally litter literal world is
also a kind of process of your own like
emotional risk because you got to kind
of get close to a lot of things that are
very difficult you know and so it's it's
it's hard stuff but I think it's also
really key because you're right once you
fall away from the from the mainstream
story and you start to go whoa things
are not we're not in Kansas anymore
inevitably those up those narratives
some of which have things are true in
them some of which are even largely true
as at least allegorically they're right
there waiting for you with all those
people and all that self reinforcing
kind of counter-narrative ready to
absorb you and if you want to stay
sovereign in the sense that I know that
that you know rebel wisdom is is partly
about that sense of being an autonomous
thinker who's moving through these
realms that aren't we're not we don't
really have a good guide for then it's
really important to be aware and process
that spiritual emotional level and
recognize what's going on in other
people because it's sort of like the
main story even though it doesn't
necessarily look like we can keep alert
to what's going on and do the work yeah
just that just a file to keep on that
keep alert to what's going on but that
your own emotions are not secondary to
that process and indeed we're being
asked to become more clear about our own
emotional processing because that's part
of both the way we get captured and it's
also part of the way that we step
forward and move
with with more coherence and enlight
great thank you very much Eric for
making the time and I'm sure we'll catch
up again soon absolutely great to be
here David thanks to Carrie rebel wisdom
was set up to make sense of the world at
a deeper level than the mainstream media
it was built for these times of crisis
and change which is why we want to do
what we can to meet the challenge of the
times more films and also for our rebel
wisdom members weekly sense-making calls
with our amazing interviewees and also
we're introducing the wisdom gym a place
to practice some of the skills that
we've talked about on the channel thanks
for watching see you soon
you